Schneider Collection
Bridgeport History Center, Bridgeport Public Library
Schneider Collection
1897-1966
c. 1900-1940
Schneider, Albert K.
BHC-MSS 0011
3 linear feet 1 manuscript box, 3 oversize boxes
Bridgeport History Center, Bridgeport Public Library
Focusing primarily on artifacts from the Barnum and Bailey Circus, the Schneider Collection contains material from the circus after the death of P.T. Barnum and into the 20th century. Photographs of the Barnum and Bailey Circus abroad also feature heavily, giving insight into what the shows were like.
Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
Purchased from the Schneiders in 1984.
Biography
Mr. Albert K. Schneider's family worked in the circus in the late 1890s and into the 1900s and beyond. His maternal grandfather William Strong painted signs, wagons, banners, and the like for the Barnum and Bailey Circus, and his step-grandfather, William Smith, worked as a veterinarian for Barnum and Bailey as well. As a result, Schneider grew up around circus people, and acquired a collection of circus material as he grew older.
Additional information about Schneider is limited, but he was involved with circus historians, as the notes regarding this acquisition mention a number of names active and involved with circus history during the 1980s. The collection was purchased from the Schneiders in 1984.
Scope and Content of Collection
Some time ago, the route books that were a part of this collection were separated out and are housed on their own.
The content of the collection is primarily souvenir material from various Barnum and Bailey Circus sojourns abroad. This includes various seasons spent in Britain, and the circus' time in Germany in 1900.
Of note, however, is the three-dimensional material. The material primarily relates to animal care, and includes files for claws and hooves, dentistry instruments, and horse related equipment.
Arrangement
Material has been grouped by circus and non-circus material, with the circus material coming first. It is then arranged by genre.
Three-dimensional items are held in two separate boxes. Most material is kept together due to size. However, the riding crops and scaler are housed separately, as the crops are made of bamboo and thus fragile, as well as the fact the items are long and thin, and thus need specialized housing.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Bailey, James Anthony, 1847-1906; Barnum and Bailey - History; Barnum and Bailey - People - 1890-1900; Barnum and Bailey - People - 1900-1910; Circus animals - pictorial works; Circus owners; Circus performers
- Inventory
  - Correspondence, 1959 and undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Menus from dinners given to the Barnum and Bailey Circuses, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Tissue paper placemats from dinners given to Barnum and Bailey Circuse, 1890s-1900s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Circus postcards, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cartes de visite of Barnum performers, 1870s-1900s (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Photograph of boat used to ship Barnum and Bailey circus to England, c. 1890s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photographs of the Barnum and Bailey Circus in Germany, 1900s (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Set of circus negatives, 1900s (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Programs from the Barnum Festival (1949, 1961, 1966), 1949-1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bridgeport Sunday Post regarding the Barnum Festival (7/8/1962) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Clippings, Barnum related, 1960s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Madame Tussaud’s exhibition, 1897 (Jenny Lind featured) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - International Universal Exhibition Guide and Catalogue, Director General Imre Kiralfy (3/12/1905) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Jenny Lind material, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Other advertisement collectibles, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Photographs of #8 firehouse and Maplewood in Bridgeport, Connecticut, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Cartes de visite, likely of Civil War soldiers, 1860s (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Photographs of Mr. and Mrs. Thomas Lynch, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Clippings, general, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Photographs of Barnum and Bailey Circus in Germany, 1900 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - “A Peep at Buffalo Bill’s Wild West” published by McLaughlin Brothers, 1887 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Pear’s Blotting Book, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook featuring clippings about Nellie Bly; Columbia Exhibition, 1890s (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Veterinarian dental tools owned by William Smith, 1900-1930 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Filing tools for claws and hooves owned by William Smith, 1900-1930 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Needle used for animal care owned by William Smith, 1900-1930 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Set of 2 horse shoes, presumably from circus horses, 1900-1930 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Training bit, presumably from circus horses, 1900-1930 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Baggage horse equipment, 1900-1930 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Pins from fire horse blankets, 1900-1930 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Tights supposedly belonging to Eliza Dockrill (Madame Dockrill), 1900-1930 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Set of pins from circus related material, 1900-1930 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Stopwatch used to time races around the ring owned by William Smith, 1900-1930 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - 2 shaving razors, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Whistle, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Stamp or paperweight with P.T. Barnum’s portrait, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Souvenir ring, 1900-1930 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Riding crops (2) owned by Todd Sloane, 1900-1930 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Scaler used to paint banners, wagons, etc. owned by Walter Strong, 1900-1930 (Box 4, Folder 2)